-==破烂熊乐园倾情奉献==-
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-==http://www.ragbear.com==-
福尔摩斯探案全集 第2季第5集
-=Keepfrds MNHD Team=-
校对: ptrpan
红发会
噢 对不起 福尔摩斯
Oh, sorry Holmes.
不 不
No, no,
你来得正是时候
you couldn't have come at a better time.
我怕你正忙呢
I was afraid you were engaged.
是的 非常忙
I am, very much so.
华生医生和我一样 热衷于稀奇古怪的东西
Dr. Watson shares my love of all that is bizarre,
而不是日常生活中那些稀松平常的老套故事
but outside the routine of everyday existence.
现在还不能断定
It is at present and impossible to say
这个案子是否属于犯罪案件
that this case is an instance of crime or no.
但是足以说
But suffice it to say that I know as little
对于杰贝斯・威尔逊先生 我和你知道的一样少
about Mr. Jay Beards Wilson as you do yourself,
除了一些明显的事实外
beyond the obvious facts.
他干过一阵儿体力活
That he has done manual labor at sometime.
曾经去过中国
But it takes staff that he has been to China.
他最近还...
And that he has done
写过不少东西
a considerable amount of writing lately.
噢!我的老天爷!
How in the name of good fortune
您怎么知道的?福尔摩斯先生
did you know all that Mr. Holmes?
真像福音一样确切 我是干过体力活
As true as gospel I once did manual labor.
我曾在船上做过木匠
I started off as a ship's carpenter.
你的手 我的好仆人
Your hands my good servant.
你右手的肌肉
The muscles of your right hand
比左手的发达
are more developed than the left.
那写作呢?
And the writing?
还有别的什么更能说明问题吗?
What else could be indicated.
右手袖子足有五寸长的地方 磨得油光发亮
By the right cuffs are very shiny for five inches.
左胳膊肘那儿打了个整洁的补丁
And the left sleeve with smooth pattern over the elbow
这是经常贴在桌面所致... 但中国?
where you lean it on the desk... but China?
右手腕正上方的鱼状纹身
The fish tattooed immediately above his right wrist.
我对纹身略有研究 威尔逊先生
I have made a small study of tattoo marks,Mr. Wilson,
我还写过...
and have even contributed to the
这方面的文章
literature of the subject.
染鱼鳞的绝技
That trick of staining the fish scales,
使用淡淡的粉红色 是中国才有的
a delicate pink is quite peculiar to China.
还有 我看见一枚中国钱币
Wherein addition I see a Chinese coin hanging
垂在他的表链上
from his watch chain.
这岂不是显然易见的吗
The matter becomes even more simple.
哈哈 真没想到...
Well I never...
起初我还觉得你真是神机妙算
I thought at first it was something clever,
说穿了 也没什么了不起
but now I see there's nothing in it after all.
我开始觉得要是心眼太实
You know I begin to think that my reputation
会毁了自己的名声
such as it is will suffer shipwreck if I'm so candid
"不为人知者乃为壮丽"
omne ignotum pro magnifico.
解释之后 一切都变得平庸
Everything becomes commonplace by explanation.
华生 这么翻译太不严谨了
Watson that is a very loose translation.
哦 请把那则广告给医生看
Oh, please show the doctor that advertisement.
哦 在这儿 您自己看吧 先生
Oh, there, you can read it for yourself sir.
红发会
To the Red Headed League.
由于原住于美国宾夕法尼亚州的
On account of the request
黎巴嫩人
of the late Iscar Hopkins of Lebanon,
伊齐基亚・霍普金斯之遗赠 现有空缺一名
Pennsylvania USA there is a vacancy open
薪金为每周四镑
which entitles a member of the league to a salary
工作则实系挂名而已
of four pounds a week for purely nominal services.
凡红发男性 身体健康 智力健全
All red headed men sound in body and mind
年满21周岁者 均可申请
and above the age of 21 are eligible.
应聘者请于星期一上午11时 亲至舰队街
Apply in person on Monday at 11:00 to Mr. Duncan Ross
教皇院7号
at the offices of the League,
红发会办公室邓肯・罗斯处提出申请
7 Copes Court Fleet Street.
此事当真?
Is this serious?
这则广告有点不合常理 华生
It is a little off the beaten track, hey Watson.
麻烦你记下报纸名和日期
Oh, would you make a note of the paper and the date?
4月27日 星期六
Evening standard of Saturday the 27th of April,
两个月前
two months ago.
请坐下
Do try this sitting.
现在 威尔逊先生 请说吧
Now, Mr. Wilson, off you go
简略地介绍一下你自己
at scratch and tell us all about yourself.
嗯 先生们 我开了个
Oh, well gentlemen I have a small
小当铺 在萨克斯科伯格广场
pawn broking business in Sax Coburg Street,
在市区附近
near the city.
买卖做得不大
It's not a very large affair.
只能勉强维持生计
It just gives me a living.
过去我还能请两个伙计 但现在只雇得起一个
I used to keep two assistants but now I just keep the one.
实话实说 我原打算付全部工钱
And to tell you the truth I'd have a job to make you pay
但这个伙计 自愿拿一半工资
but the deeds willing to come at half wages
说是为了学做生意
so as to learn the business.
大约两个月前...
About two months ago...
这个热心肠的小伙子叫什么?
What is the name of the obliging youth?
文森特・斯波尔丁
Vincent Spalding.
但他算不上是个小伙子 福尔摩斯先生
Oh, but he's not such a youth either Mr. Holmes.
我不太清楚他的年纪
It's difficult to say his age
可我再也找不到比这个 更精明能干的伙计了
but I couldn't wish for a smarter assistant.
你的运气真不赖!
You seem most remarkably fortunate.
以低于市价的工钱雇到伙计
In having an employee who comes under the market price,
不知道你那个伙计
I don't know that your assistant
是不是同那则广告 一样非比寻常?
is not as remarkable as your advertisement.
哦 他也有缺点
Oh, but he does have his faults.
他比谁都爱照相
However, he was such a fellow for photography.
整天拿着相机到处拍照
Always snapping away with his camera
不愿在工作上动脑筋 然后钻进...
when he should be improving his mind and then diving down
地下室去冲洗那些东西
into the cellar to develop the wretched things.
但是 总的来说 他算是个好伙计
Still on the whole he's a good worker.
没什么坏心眼
No vice in him.
当初就是他 把广告拿给我看的
It was he who first showed me the advertisement.
但愿我是红头发 威尔逊先生
I wish to the lord I was a red headed man Mr. Wilson.
为什么?
Why is that?
现在红发会里
Well there's another vacancy
又有职位空缺了
in the League of Red Headed Men.
从未听过这事儿
I've never heard of it.
我还纳闷呢 您本人就非常符合资格
Well, I'd wonder at that you being so eligible yourself.
薪金相当可观
Nice money too.
一年200镑 活儿又轻松...
A couple hundred a year and the work's light...
到时可得有成千上万的 红发人去应聘吧
Oh, there'll be thousands of red headed men apply.
我可不这么认为 先生
Oh, well I doubt that sir.
没人有你这么火红的头发...
Well nobody with such a fine fiery color
如同上天恩赐一般 威尔逊先生
as you're blessed with Mr. Wilson.
但是我想还是不值得
But then I suppose it's only worth your while
为了那几百英镑
to put yourself out of the way
特地跑一趟吧
for sake of a few hundred pounds.
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
嗯 我很爱呆在家里
Well I'm very much of a stay at home sort of person.
有时候连续几个星期 我都不会踏出门口半步
Sometimes weeks on end before I put my foot over the doormat
但这个看起来很有意思
but this it looked interesting.
我对此很感兴趣 而年轻的文森特...
I was intrigued and young Vincent
说他愿意陪我一起去
said he'd come with me.
所以星期一早上 我们锁好店门
So, on Monday morning we shut up the shop
便动身了
and off we went.
文森特 我们回去吧
Now, Vincent let's go back
人太多 过不去
I can't get by the crowd.
拿出勇气 威尔逊先生
Courage Mr. Wilson.
我们就快到了 正处在重要关头
We're so near and so much at stake.
现在穿上外套
Now you put your coat on
跟着我走
and come along with me.
喂 喂 喂 请小点声
Ohy, Ohy, Ohy, a little less noise
先生们
please gentlemen.
这里 看这里 你什么意思?
Here, here what's your game?
喂 滚开
Hey get out of here.
喂...喂...
Hey, hey...
你可以走了 你是下一个 进去吧
Off you go, you next, get in.
嘿 你往哪儿走?
Hey, where are you going?
这边直走 走吧
Straight this way, Come on.
这位是威尔逊先生
This is Mr. Wilson.
直接进去吧 威尔逊先生
Right in you go Mr. Wilson.
非常合适
Admirably suited.
完全符合要求
Every requirement.
静下来了
Very quiet.
恭喜您 威尔逊先生
Congratulations Mr. Wilson.
再迟疑就太不对了
It would be injustice to hesitate.
您不介意我采取谨慎措施吧?
You will I'm sure excuse me if I take an obvious precaution.
眼泪都流出来了
Tears in your eyes.
想必是真头发了
I perceive all is as it should be.
我们不得不小心防范
We have to be careful.
被假发骗过两次 被颜料骗过一次
Twice deceived by wigs, once by paint.
还有用鞋蜡来玩花招的
I could tell you tales of cobblers wags
您听了准会感到恶心
that would disgust you with human nature.
我叫邓肯・罗斯
My name is Duncan Ross.
我自己就是基金的受益人
I am myself a pension upon a fund left by
这是一位尊贵的捐赠者遗留的
a noble benefactor.
就知道你要问我 伊乔基亚・霍普金斯先生的事
I see you're about to question me about Mr. Ethic Guya Hopkins.
他自己长了一头红发
He was himself red headed.
他年轻时离开伦敦去了美国
In his youth he left London for America where he made
赚了好几百万美元
many millions of dollars.
他死后 人们发现他曾立下遗嘱
On his death it was found that he had instructed
吩咐财产托管人让他出生的这座城市中
a trustee in his will to make life a little easier
生活着的红发人日子过得舒适安逸
for the red headed men in the town of his birth.
绝妙的颜色
Wonderful color.
您的全名叫什么?  威尔逊先生
Now what's your full name Mr. Wilson?
杰贝斯・威尔逊
Jay Beards Wilson.
杰贝斯・威尔逊 您结婚了吗?
Jay Beards Wilson and are you a married man,
威尔逊先生?
Mr. Wilson?
你有妻儿吗?
Do you have a family?
没有 我是个鳏夫
No, I'm a widower.
不 我从来就没有过什么家人
No, I never had any family.
哎呀 真遗憾听您这么说
Oh dear, sad to hear you say that.
本基金设立的目的就是为了...
The fund of course is for the propagation
红发人更多地繁衍
and spread of red headed men
延续他们的血脉
as well as with their maintenance.
要是换了别人 这个缺点可能是不幸的
In another case the objection might be fatal.
但我想我们得破例照顾一下
However, I've think we've got to stretch a point
因为您的头发长得这么好
in favor of a man with such a head of hair as yours.
空缺已经有人了
The vacancy has been filled.
空缺有人了
The vacancy is filled.
现在请离开吧
Now, off you go.
不好意思
Sorry about that.
走吧
Off you go.
您什么时候可以来上班?
Now, when would you be free to start upon your new duties?
嗯 这事还有点不好办 因为我本身也有做买卖
Oh, well it is rather awkward as I do have a business already.
什么时候上班?
What would be the hours?
上午10点到下午2点
10:00 to 2:00.
上午生意倒清淡
Well the mornings are quiet.
我也有个伙计帮忙照看
I do have an assistant.
嗯 对我来说很合适
Yes, that would suit me very well.
薪水是每周四英镑?
And the money mentioned, four pounds a week.
没错
Correct.
干些什么活?
And the work?
纯属挂名
Purely nominal.
纯属挂名是什么意思?
Yes, but what do you call purely nominal?
就是说您必须待在办公室里
Well, you have to stay in the office
至少在工作时间内呆在这栋楼里
or at least in the building the whole time.
一旦离开 便会 永远丢掉这个职位
If you leave you forfeit your whole position forever.
对于这一点 遗嘱写得很清楚
The will is quite clear on that point.
噢 我不会离开的
Oh, I shouldn't dream of leaving.
任何借口都没用
No, excuse will avail.
不管是生病 有事  还是其他原因都不行
Not a sickness, business, anything else.
您必须待在这里 否则会丢掉这份工作
Here you will remain or else lose your ability.
哦 我清楚明白了
Oh, I am quite clear on that point.
具体的工作内容是什么呢?
But what exactly is the work?
您的工作是抄写
It is to copy out the encyclopedia Britannica.
这是第一卷
There is the first volume.
您得自备笔墨纸砚
You will supply the ink, paper and pen.
我们只提供桌椅
We will supply this desk and chair.
下星期一能开始上班吗?
Now would you be free to start next Monday morning?
是的 当然可以
Oh, yes, certainly.
那么再次祝贺您
Then once again my congratulations
杰贝斯・威尔逊先生 得到这个重要职务
Mr. Jay Beards Wilson on the most important position
你很幸运!
you've been fortunate enough to gain.
真是完美的头发!
Wonderful head of hair.
再见 威尔逊先生
Good bye Mr. Wilson.
干得好 威尔逊先生
Well done Mr. Wilson.
干得非常好!
Well done indeed.
这条路最近 先生
This is the quickest way out sir.
哦
Oh.
这边走
This way.
我回到家仔细一想
When I got home the whole thing seemed
整件事情太荒谬了
on reflection to be quite ridiculous.
为什么?
Why?
谁会立下这样不寻常的遗嘱呢?
Who would make such an extraordinary will?
一个如此慷慨的百万富翁
Not a very generous millionaire to make you
竟让你自备笔墨纸砚
buy your own pen, ink, and paper.
就是说嘛 福尔摩斯先生
Exactly Mr. Holmes.
很快我便说服自己 这一定是个大骗局
I soon persuaded myself it was some great hoax or fraud.
但到了星期一早上 又觉得只有笨蛋才会
And then when Monday morning came along it seemed stupid
拒绝这样的好工作
to turn down a good job
所以 我去买了一瓶 一个便士的墨水
so, off I went and bought a penny bottle of ink
一只羽毛笔和七张大书写纸
and a pen and seven sheets of fools kept paper.
前往教皇院
And I set off for Popes Core.
早上好 威尔逊先生 欢迎您
Good morning, Mr. Wilson and welcome.
早上好
Good morning.
让我又惊又喜的是
Well to my surprise and delight
一切都很顺利
everything was as right as possible.
桌椅都摆好了
The table was set up ready for me
邓肯・罗斯先生也在那儿 等我了解工作内容后
and Mr. Duncan Ross was there to see I got fairly to work.
我的工作也就真正开始了
My employment had truly begun.
每天都是如此
The schedule never varied.
从早上10点开始干活 下午2点离开
My work started at 10:00 and ended at 2:00
12点半的时候有一小段时间吃午餐
with a small break for my lunch at half past 12:00.
每星期六下午2点 罗斯先生都会过来
Every Saturday at 2:00 Mr. Ross would come in
发给我一个星期的薪水
and give me my money.
称赞我抄写得真不赖
Compliment me upon the amount that I'd written
然后我们一起离开
and then we'd both leave.
最后罗斯先生把门锁上
Mr. Ross locking the door afterwards.
我发现朝鲜蓟非常迷人
The artichokes I found were positively fascinating.
他们也开花
They have a kind of a bloom on them but...
我觉得很有趣...
I thought that was very interesting...
再回
Good Morning.
噢 这份工作很有意思
Oh, the work was very interesting.
算盘
Abacus,
修道院
abbey,
建筑
architecture,
acts of the Apostles,
劣质品
adulteration,
解剖学
anatomy,
大猩猩
apes,
罗马引水道
aquaducts.
八个星期一晃而过 我差不多抄完...
After eight weeks I'd fairly dealt with
以字母A开头的词条了 期望通过不懈努力
the letter "A" and was hoping the diligence
早日抄到B开头的词条 但今天早上
to get onto "B" when suddenly this morning
整件事情突然结束了
the whole business came to end.
我像往常一样去上班 发现门关着 锁了
I went to my work as usual but the door was shut
上面还有一张方形的卡片
and locked with a little square of cardboard
用图钉钉在门板中央
hammered onto the middle panel.
红发会即日起解散
打扰一下
Oh, excuse me.
您今天早上有见过邓肯・罗斯先生吗?
Have you seen Mr. Duncan Ross this morning?
罗斯 罗斯?
Ross, Ross?
从未听说过这个人 先生
Never heard of a gentleman with that name, sir
我记性很好的
and my memory is good.
没错 不会错的
It's very good, it's infallible to me.
不 7号办公室的那位先生
No, the gentleman in number seven.
哦 那位红头发的先生?
Ah, the gentleman who is red headed?
是的 没错
Yes, yes.
哦 对 对 对 走了
Uh, yes, yes, yes, gone.
走了?
Gone?
威廉・莫里斯先生 是一名律师
Mr. William Morris, solicitor using my room as
在他的办公室布置好之前暂时租用我的房间
a temporary convenience until his new premises were ready.
昨天就搬走了 房租也付清了 一分都不少
Moved out yesterday, paid in full, doesn't owe a penny.
莫里斯先生 我上哪儿可以找到他?
Mr. Morris, where can I find him?
到他的新办公室
At his new offices.
威廉・莫里斯...
William Morris...
爱德华国王街17号
17 King Edwards Street,
在圣保罗教堂附近
near St. Paul's.
谢谢你
Oh, thank you.
巴基父子护膝制造厂
我不觉得这有什么好笑的
I don't see that there's anything very funny about it.
如果你们只会笑话我 我可以另请高明
If all you can do is laugh at me well I can go elsewhere.
不 威尔逊先生 请坐
No, Mr. Wilson please, please sit down.
我绝对不会错过这个案子的
I wouldn't miss this case for the world.
这太不寻常了
It is most refreshingly unusual.
被人这样欺骗 我气到不行
I was so incensed with the forgery of deceit
所以直接就来找你了
that I came straight to you sir.
我听说你很乐意
Having heard of your great reputation
为需要帮助的人出谋划策
for helping poor people in distress.
威尔逊先生
Mr. Wilson.
威尔逊先生 我真的觉得你不该
You know Mr. Wilson I really don't think that you've got
抱怨这个极不寻常的红发会
any great grievance against this extraordinary league.
正好相反 您倒赚不少钱
On the contrary you've been very well paid to say nothing
更不用说您长了见识
of the detailed knowledge which you've acquired
熟知了全部字母A为首的词条
on every subject under the letter A.
是的 但他们为什么要对我开这个大玩笑?
Yes, but what's the object of them playing this prank on me?
这就是我想知道的
That is what I want to know.
你那个伙计 在你那儿干了多久?
This assistant of yours, how long has he been with you?
大约三个月
Well about three months.
他是怎么来的?
How did he come?
看广告应征
With the answer to an advertisement.
他是唯一的应征者?
Was he the only applicant?
不是 还有12个
No, I had 12 others.
那你为什么选他?
Why did you pick him?
因为他勤快 要的工钱也低
Well he was handy and would come cheap.
事实上 只要一半工资
At half wages in fact.
是的
Yes.
这个文森特・斯波尔丁 长什么模样?
What's he like, this Vincent Spalding?
瘦高个子
Oh, well he's tall, slightly built
动作敏捷
and he's very quick in his ways.
未蓄胡须
He's got no hair on his face.
前额上有块被硫酸烧伤的白色伤疤
He's got a white splash of acid on his forehead.
你有没有注意到他耳朵上
Uh, have you ever observed whether his ears
有戴耳环用的穿孔?
have been pierced for earrings?
有 有 他说一个吉普赛人
Yes, yes, he told me a gypsy
在他年少时给他穿的孔
had done it for him when he was a lad.
他还在你那里?
He is still with you?
是的 我刚离开他不久
Yes, I just left him.
威尔逊先生 你会在店里吧?
Mr. Wilson, You will be at your shop
我找你的时候
if I should need you?
我想过晚餐的时候歇业休息
Well I had thought of shutting up shop
因为文森特建议我
at dinner time today because Vincent had suggested
去巴金与我妹妹
I spend the rest of the weekend
共度周末
with my sister in Barking.
整件事令我 精神极度紧张
This whole business has upset my nerves very much.
这个周末你可以 在巴金好好放松一下
Well you enjoy a restful weekend in Barking.
今天是星期六
Today's Saturday.
星期一我们即可做出结论
By Monday we should have a conclusion for you.
关于咨询费的问题...
In the matter of your fee...
别担心
Don't worry about that.
相信有人会替你付的
I believe it will be paid for by another.
祝你今天过得愉快 威尔逊先生
Good day to you Mr. Wilson.
华生 你怎么看?
What do you make of it all Watson?
我什么也没看出来
I make nothing of it.
这事儿太玄乎了
Most mysterious business.
但是还有更大的阴谋
Yet there are graver issues
隐藏在这件事情背后
hanging from this affair then that first had appeared.
接下来你打算怎么办?
What are you going to do?
抽烟
To smoke.
得抽三斗烟的时间才能解决
It is quite a three pipe problem
50分钟内请不要和我搭话
and I beg that you won't speak to me for 50 minutes.
红发会事件
The business of the Red Headed League
已经结束了 先生
is concluded sir.
我相信一定能圆满解决
Satisfactorily I trust.
非常令人满意 很高兴向您汇报
Most satisfactorily professor I am pleased to report.
好
Good.
来 华生
Come Watson.
啊?
Huh?
劳驾
Excuse me.
请问从这儿到河滨大街怎么走?
Can you tell me the way to the Strand from here?
在第三个路口右拐 到第四个路口左拐 先生
Uh, third right, fourth left sir.
谢谢
Thank you.
福尔摩斯?
Holmes?
福尔摩斯 我都可以告诉你
Holmes, I could have told you that.
毫无疑问 华生
No doubt, Watson.
怎么了?
What is it?
你为何用手杖敲人行道?
And why did you beat the pavement with your stick?
华生 我们在敌人的领地侦察
Watson we are spies in an enemy's territory.
这是我的爱好
It's a hobby of mine
熟悉伦敦每一次细微的地方
to have an exact knowledge of London.
这里有一家莫蒂麦烟草店
Now there's Mortimore's, the tobacconist.
一个小售报摊
The little newspaper shop.
城市和郊区银行的科伯格分行
Coburg Branch, the City and Suburban Bank.
麦克法兰马车制造厂
McFarland's Carriage Building Depot
转角处有一家素食店
and the vegetarian restaurant around the corner.
华生 想想刚才的情景 我们有可能
Watson commit to memory, it's just possible
正被人监视着
that we're being observed.
一个大罪案即将发生
A considerable crime's in contemplation.
今天是星期六 在某程度上使事情更为复杂
Today being Saturday somewhat complicates matters.
但是现在 医生... 工作已经完成
But now doctor... our work is done.
是时候消遣了
It is time we had some play.
萨拉萨蒂(西班牙小提琴家)下午在 圣詹姆斯会堂表演
Sarasate's playing at Sir James Hall this afternoon.
先来份三明治和一杯咖啡?
A sandwich and a cup of coffee?
然后去小提琴演奏厅
And then off to violin land with all
感受美妙而优雅的气氛
its sweetness, delicacy and harmony.
没有红头发委托人 出难题困扰我们
And no red headed clients to vex us with their conundrums.
他整个下午都坐在观众席
All the afternoon he sat in the stalls
沉醉在欢乐的意境中
wrapped in the most perfect happiness
他满脸的微笑 迷离的眼神
while his gently smiling face, and his languid dreamy eyes
和做大侦探时的福尔摩斯
were as unlike those of Holmes the sleuth hound
神态迥异 判若两人
as it was possible to conceive.
看着他完全融入音乐当中
When I saw him so enwrapped in music
我觉得一个邪恶的时刻可能即将来临
I felt that an evil time might be coming upon those
而他会追查到底
he had set himself to hunt down.
精彩绝伦 华生
Excellent Watson.
你有做制图师的才华
You have a future as a cartographer.
那是阿瑟尔尼・琼斯侦探
That will be Athelney Jones.
我认为有苏格兰场的人
I thought it was well enough to have someone
与我们同往比较好
from Scotland Yard with us.
他在侦探这个行业 算是个低能儿
He's an absolute imbecile at his profession
但抓人的时候顽强得像只大龙虾
but he does the tenacity of a lobster when he gets
一遇到罪犯就紧抓不放
his claws into someone.
晚上好 琼斯
Good evening Jones.
我们又成为搭档了 福尔摩斯先生
So we're working in couples again,Mr. Holmes.
我们这位朋友是个追猎高手
Our friend is a wonderful man for starting a chase.
他所需的仅是一条 帮他捕获猎物的老狗
All he needs is an old dog to help him do the running down.
梅里韦瑟先生 我的朋友和同事华生医生
Mr. Merryweather, my friend and college Dr. Watson.
你好 先生
How do you do sir?
我只希望我们的追捕
I only hope a wild goose may not prove
不要徒劳无功
to be the end of our chase.
就我个人而言 并不看好
I'm not personally in favor
业余犯罪调查
of amateur criminal investigation.
你应该对福尔摩斯先生充满信心
You might place considerable confidence in Mr. Holmes.
既然您这么说 琼斯先生
Oh, if you say so Mr. Jones.
他自有一套办法 要是他不介意...
He has his own little methods, which if he won't
我这么说 有点过于理论化
mind me saying so a little theoretical
和妙想天开 但他倒是具有...
and fantastic, but he has the makings
...侦探的素质
of a detective in him.
但我还是要说 正如我说过的
But I do say as I've said before
科伯格分行非常安全
the Colburg Branch of the Bank is as well secured
如伦敦任一座楼房一样
as any building in London.
它是不可能被破门而入的
There isn't a possibility that it could be broken into.
连保险公司顾问都这样说
Even insurance assessors agree on that point.
而先生 你应该知道
And you sir should know
作为银行经理和董事
being not only the resident manager but also the director.
我应该知道 并且确实知道
I should know and I do know.
还有 这可是我27年来
And what is more, this is the first time
头一次错过
for seven and twenty years that I've missed my
俱乐部的周六威士忌之夜
Saturday night of whiskey at my club.
对我造成很大的不便啊
And I find myself extremely inconvenienced.
我想你会发现 今晚的行动
I think that you will find the game tonight
更加刺激 赌注将会是
much more exciting and the stake will be
好几千英镑
for many, many thousands of pounds.
我的奖赏是什么呢? 福尔摩斯先生
And what will be my reward be Mr. Homes?
一位年轻人 名叫克莱
A young man, called Clay.
约翰・克莱？
John Clay?
噢 我真想抓住那个恶魔
Oh, how I'd like to get my hands on that devil.
你会的
You shall.
福尔摩斯先生所说这个年轻人是个绅士
This young fellow's a gentleman as Mr. Holmes says
但背叛了自己的阶层
but he's turned against his class.
如恶魔般狡诈
He's as cunning as the devil.
如鳝鱼般圆滑 把杀人和诈骗
Slippery as an eel and he's turned crib cracking
当作一门艺术
and forgery into a fine art.
其祖父是王室公爵
His grandfather was a royal duke
他本人曾在伊顿公学 和牛津大学念过书
and he himself was educated at Eaton and Oxford.
所以 华生 带上枪
So Watson, bring the gun.
走吧 先生们 马车就在楼下
Come gentlemen our cab is below.
保险库的钥匙只有两把
There are only two keys to the vault.
我有一把 行长有一把
I have one, the chairman holds the other
放在他的私人保险柜里
in his personal safe.
从上面攻进来相当困难
Well you are certainly not vulnerable from above.
从下面来也是
Nor from below.
稍等一下
Just a minute.
请您小声一点
I'm going to ask you to be a little more quiet please.
请您找个箱子坐下
Might I get you to sit on one of those boxes
别乱动
and not to interfere?
根本不可能有小偷
There is no way in which a thief
能够强行闯入银行
could break into this bank.
有什么特殊原因使得小偷
Is there a special reason why a thief
想要强行闯入这个银行吗?
should want to break into this bank?
没什么特别的...
Nothing particularly...
过去几个月进来的东西呢?
Something in the past few months?
你想对我们隐藏的事?
Something that you had concealed from us?
这是机密信息
The information I have is confidential
只有银行董事才知道
known only to the directors of the bank.
不能把它泄露给公众
It is not to be divulged to members of the public,
业余侦探也不行
not even amateur detectives.
是私人顾问侦探 梅里韦瑟先生
Private consulting detective, Mr. Merryweather.
在打击犯罪上独一无二
Unique in the annuls of crime I believe,
难道不是吗 警官?
isn't that so inspector?
是的 医生
Yes, doctor.
我建议你与福尔摩斯先生合作
I advise you to cooperate with Mr. Holmes.
尤其在这个时候 我正想法设法帮你
Especially as at this moment I am trying to save your skin
和其他董事度过危机
and that of your fellow directors.
那么到底是什么?
So what is it?
我们的法国黄金
Our French gold.
几个月前我们恰好有机会增加资金来源
We had occasion some months ago to strengthen our resources
从法兰西银行
and borrowed for that purpose 60,000 Napoleons
借了6万拿破仑金币(一块拿破仑金币值20法郎)
from the bank of France.
所以我们的黄金储备就比
Therefore our reserve of bullion is much larger than is usual
其他分行多很多
in such a branch of the bank.
这些金币在哪?
Where is this gold?
华生医生坐的那些大箱子里
The crates upon which Dr. Watson sits
装着3万拿破仑金币
contain 30,000 Napoleons
用铅箔一层一层包着
wrapped between layers of lead foil.
我们可以看看吗?
May we see it?
这比我当初所想
This is much bolder and larger in conception
更大胆 更大规模 难道不是吗 琼斯?
than I had first thought, wouldn't you say Jones?
确实是的
I would indeed.
这位克莱更像个业余探险家
This Clay's more of an amateur adventurer
或是冲动型罪犯
or spur of the moment criminal,
长期计划不是克莱的风格 一点都不是
Long planning is not Clay's type at all sir, not at all.
除非他是别人手中的棋子
Unless he's a pawn in a much larger game.
梅里韦瑟先生 有人探知...
Mr. Merryweather someone has had access to
你最机密的信息
information of the most confidential sort.
制定了周密详尽的计划
Careful plans have been made.
这是经人精心筹划的
A mastermind has been at work.
你是说...
Are you suggesting that...
我是说这非常像
I am suggesting that it bears the hallmarks
莫里亚蒂教授的手段
of Professor Moriarity's work.
莫里亚蒂?
Moriarity?
莫里亚蒂是谁?
And who is this Moriarity?
我们并不清楚 先生
We don't really know sir.
我和警方都不曾想到
That is neither the police nor I think
夏洛克・福尔摩斯先生已经在盯着他
Mr. Sherlock Holmes here has ever set eyes on him.
他的名字在黑社会人所皆知
His name echoes and re-echoes throughout the underworld.
显然他出身高贵
It appears that he's a man of good birth,
受过极好的教育 但是他继承了...
an excellent education but he has hereditary
恶魔般的特质
tendencies of the most diabolical kind.
血液里充斥着犯罪的因子
A criminal strain runs in his blood
日趋严重 变得相当危险
which has increased and rendered infinitely more dangerous
因为他的智力 非比寻常
by his extraordinary mental powers.
他组织了这座城市中
He's the organizer of half that is evil and nearly all that
半数罪案和几乎所有未被识破的案件
is undetected in this great city.
却一直逍遥法外
He is never caught.
他有手下被抓 但作为中坚力量的他...
His agent is caught but the central power
一直逍遥法外 甚至没有被怀疑过
is never caught certainly even suspected.
教授今晚是不会出现了
We shall not see the professor tonight.
今晚的敌人的唯一退路是...
The only way for tonight's enemy to escape is through
经由当铺逃窜
the pawn brokers.
已经有一个警官守在门口了
There's already an inspector at the doors.
没错
Exactly.
时间差不多到了... 各就各位...
We have only a few moments... positions...
能麻烦你把灯关掉吗?
Would you be so kind as to put out this lamp.
然后坐在黑暗中?
And sit in the dark?
恐怕是的
I'm afraid so.
我们不能冒险发出亮光
We cannot risk the presence of light.
一旦我亮出灯光 动作迅速...
When I shine the light, act swiftly...
要是他们肆无忌惮的开枪
If they fire have no compassion
马上击毙他们
about shooting them down.
噢 天哪!
Great god.
快逃 快
Jump at it, jump.
没用的 约翰・克莱
It's no good jump John Clay.
你逃不掉了
You have no chance at all.
明白了...
So I see...
但我的同伴会没事
though I fancy my pal's all right.
现在他正跑向...
At this moment he is running into
警察的环抱中
the welcoming arms of the police.
你做得还真是天衣无缝
You seem to have done the thing very completely.
我该称赞你才对
I must compliment you.
你也一样
And I you.
我是夏洛克・福尔摩斯 私人侦探
I'm Sherlock Holmes, a private investigator.
我从没怀疑过你是...
I didn't for a moment suspect your being
警察 福尔摩斯先生
a policeman Mr. Holmes.
得了吧 回去再聊
Come on, hold that one off for the Darby's.
别用你那脏手碰我
I beg you to take your filthy hands off me.
你们不知道我的血管里流着皇家血统吗
You may not be aware that I have royal blood
请你们跟我说话的时候
in my veins and be so kind as to say "sir" and "please"
都要用"先生"和"请"
when you address me.
那好
All right.
请先生上台阶吧
Would you please sir, mind marching upstairs
我们会用马车将阁下
while we get a cab to transport your highness
送到警署
to the police station?
这还差不多
That's better.
先生们
Gentlemen.
噢 有个问题 克莱先生
Oh, one question Mr. Clay.
莫里亚蒂教授是否...
Am I right in thinking that professor Moriarity
策划了红发会事件?
was somewhere behind the idea of the Red Headed League?
我建议你再也不要提起 这个名字 福尔摩斯先生
I suggest you keep that name off your lips Mr. Holmes
要是你还想将来活得好好的话
if you value your future well-being.
真的 先生们 我都不知道说什么好了
Really gentlemen, I don't know what to say.
请原谅我 福尔摩斯先生 我竟怀疑过
Please forgive me Mr. Holmes for ever doubting
你的神机妙算 经天纬地之才
your outstanding, your brilliant qualities.
毫无疑问 你用最完美的方式
There is no doubt you've detected and defeated
侦查并破获了这起严谨周密的案件
in the most complete manner one of the boldest attempts
银行盗窃案 真是闻所未闻
at bank robbery that has ever come within my experience.
梅里韦瑟先生 这件事情上我有点破费
Mr. Merryweather I have then some small expense over this matter
希望银行能给予补偿
I shall expect the bank to refund.
当然 当然
Of course, of course.
你不会是早知道...
It won't do you know...
这样行不通吧
it won't do.
不 教授
No Professor.
抱歉 我们令您失望了
I'm sorry we failed you.
夏洛克・福尔摩斯...
Sherlock Holmes...
福尔摩斯在侦探这行只是个外行
Holmes is a mere amateur in the field of detection.
但他看起来是个聪明人 或是运气不错
Still he seems a clever man or a lucky one
还有碍我事的本领
and he has a positive talent for getting in my way.
要除掉他吗?
Should he be removed?
可能有这个必要
It may be necessary.
但会令人失望
It would be disappointing.
我觉得他很有意思
I find him interesting.
我相信这是他第三次
I believe this is the third time
给我添麻烦了
he has incommoded me.
如果再继续下去 那么当然要...
If this continues then certainly something
做点什么来刺激一下福尔摩斯先生
will have to be done to encourage Mr. Holmes
让他要么离开 要么靠边站
either to withdraw or stand clear.
谢谢
Thank you.
早上好 治安官
Morning Constable.
请原谅 华生医生
Beg your pardon Dr. Watson
但这一切太让人难以承受了
but this has all been too much for me.
顾客都敬重我 因我值得信赖
My clients respect me as a man of confidence
但我现在还有什么自信!
but where's the confidence left here.
我全毁了...
I'm utterly ruined...
噢 开心点 威尔逊先生
Oh, cheer up Mr. Wilson.
等清理完残局后 会感觉好点的
You'll feel better when you've cleared up the mess.
你说的是很对...
Well that's all very well...
福尔摩斯先生 让我把这个给您
And Mr. Holmes asked me to give you this,
50块金币 (价值75英镑)
50 sovereigns with the compliments
城市和郊区银行敬赠
of the City and Suburban Bank.
嗯 太好了
Well that's fair enough.
噢 华生医生 这比我的期望好太多了
Oh, Dr. Watson, this is more than acceptable,
请代我问候夏洛克・福尔摩斯先生
and my compliments to Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
他也向你致意 威尔逊先生
And he sends the same to you Mr. Wilson
一点忠告...
and a word of advice...
下次你雇用伙计时
Next time you engage an assistant
付他适当的薪水
pay him the proper wage.
再见
Good day to you.
噢 福尔摩斯 我确信自己
Oh, Holmes, I trust I am not more dense
并不比别人笨拙 可我看到...
than my neighbors and yet here I have seen
你所看到的 听到你所听到的
what you have seen, heard what you have heard
然而你不仅对已经发生的事情了如指掌
and yet you have seen clearly not only what had happened,
而且还知道将要发生什么 可我仍然觉得自己
but what was about to happen while to me the whole business
一头雾水 不知道发生什么事
was still confused and grotesque.
华生医生 回想一下
Dr. Watson recollect,
当我听到那个伙计只要求一半薪水时
when I heard that the assistant had come for half wages,
很明显他带着某种目的
it was obvious that he had some motive
为确保事情在他掌控之中
for securing the situation.
可你如何猜透他的动机?
Yes, but how did you know what his motive was?
倘若那个当铺有女人
Had there been a woman in the house I would have
我会怀疑不过是些庸俗的风流事
suspected immediately if some vulgar intrigue,
但当我听到威尔逊先生说起
but when I heard from Mr. Wilson
硫酸烧伤的疤和打过耳洞的耳朵
about the acid stain and the pierced ears
我就知道文森特・斯波尔丁和约翰・克莱
I knew that Vincent Spalding and John Clay
是同一个人
were the same person.
克莱为什么在那里呢？
But why was Clay there?
照相就是线索所在
The photography gave you the clue.
是的
Exactly.
地下室 他在地下室做着某种勾当
The cellar, he was working on something in the cellar.
每天都干好几个小时
Something which took many hours a day
整整两个月 肯定是在挖地道 但通向哪里呢？
for two months on end. He was tunneling but where to?
那天我用手杖敲打人行道时
When I tapped my stick on the pavement
不过想弄清楚
in the street that day I was ascertaining
结果那条地道是从前面通向房子后面
whether the tunnel stretched in front or behind the building.
它在前边 是朝后延伸的
It was in front, towards the back.
从这儿到河滨大街怎么走?
Could you tell me the way to the strand from here?
我立即便认出是克莱 并拖延了他的时间
I recognized Clay immediately and delayed him
仔细观察了他的膝盖
to have time to examine his knees.
显然他花了很多时间挖隧道
There he spoke clearly of many hours or tunneling.
毫无疑问连通了错综复杂的下水道
No doubt linking up with a maze of sewers
就在萨克斯科伯格广场下面
beneath Saxe Coburg Square.
他们关闭红发会办公室时
When they closed the Red Headed League offices,
就标志着他们不再在意
it was a sign they no longer cared about
杰贝斯・威尔逊是否在当铺里
Jay Beards Wilson's presence.
换句话说 地道已经挖通了
In other words the tunnel was complete.
他们会在星期六采取行动
And that they would make the attempt on a Saturday
只是猜测？
was just a guess?
华生 你令我失望了
Watson, you disappoint me.
我从不猜测
I never guess.
星期六晚上偷盗金块 是再好不过的
Saturday's an excellent night for stealing bullion.
这样便有一整天时间逃跑
It gives you a full day to escape.
请拿好 慢走
Thank you then.
有劳
Thank you.
你的讲解真是精彩绝伦 福尔摩斯
Oh, you've reasoned it out beautifully Holmes.
就像一根长长的链条 每一个环节都天衣无缝
It's so long a chain and yet every link rings true.
这样我才不会无聊
It saved me from irony.
有时我觉得我这一生
You know sometimes I think my whole life is spent
都在苦苦挣扎以摆脱
in one long effort to escape from
庸碌平凡
the common places of existence.
不 不
No, no.
您是个福泽人间的精英 福尔摩斯
You are a benefactor of the race Holmes.
哦 也许小有用处吧
Well maybe it is of some little use after all.
人是渺小的 著作就是一切
"L'homme c'est rien...l'oeuvre c'est tout"
正如居斯塔夫・福楼拜写信给乔治・桑时所言
as Gusta Flabare wrote to George Sand.
破烂熊字幕组
-==http://www.ragbear.com==-
欢迎加入